Michael John Schmidt Schmidtyworks@gmail.com

Profile:

I am a Wildlife Biologist with six years of experience managing habitat for endangered, threatened, candidate and sensitive wildlife species on federal lands. My responsibilities as a supervisory land manager have given me the skills to efficiently manage complex workloads by myself or in a team environment.

Education:

Fort Lewis College

Durango, Colorado Bachelor of Science in Environmental Biology Class of 2008

Employment:

U.S. Department of the Interior - Bureau of Land Management

Southwest District, Tres Rios Field Office June 2014 – August 2014 Wildlife Biologist – Detail (GS-0486-09) Supervisor – Nate West; Phone: 970-882-6835

- Analyzed land action affects to threatened, endangered, and sensitive species. Made wildlife management recommendations in Environmental Assessments (EA) and Wildlife Clearances as part of the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) process.
- Interpreted Colorado Parks and Wildlife (CPW) and Bureau of Land Management (BLM) spatial wildlife data to complete wildlife clearances and contribute wildlife analysis to EAs.
- Participated on interdisciplinary teams as a wildlife biologist for multiple projects including fuels reductions projects, land acquisitions, 3D seismic projects and applications for permit to drill.
- Made recommendations on the behalf of the BLM to the Colorado Department of Transportation on planning wildlife crossings along the Highway 160 corridor.
- Completed Emergency Stabilization and Fire Rehabilitation project to clean out stock ponds and water catchments that had been filled with sediment after the Weber Fire in Mancos, Colorado.
- Coordinated with CPW to complete a piñon-juniper habitat improvement project for Gunnison sage-grouse in Dry Creek Basin, CO.
- Worked with Southwest Conservation Corps, a local non-profit, to hire wildlife interns through a statewide agreement.

- Attended a BLM Gunnison sage-grouse Colorado plan amendment public meeting in Dove Creek, Colorado.
- Led a team to develop and build ArcGIS wildlife databases to catalog completed Mexican spotted owl surveys and active bat locations.

U.S. Department of Agriculture - Forest Service

San Juan National Forest, Dolores-Mancos District March 2012-Present Biological Technician Supervisor (GS-0404-07, 18/8 appointment) Supervisor – Ivan Messinger; Phone: 970-882-6804

- Performed NEPA wildlife clearances. This involved conducting a review of project area records and biological files in order to make recommendations to mitigate disturbance to threatened, endangered, candidate and sensitive species prior to and during project implementation for Forest Service (FS) categorically excluded projects.
- Planned and conducted field inventories for Mexican spotted owls, Gunnison sage-grouse, golden eagles, northern goshawks, peregrine falcons, boreal toads, big horn sheep, several bat species and several fish species.
- Designed and planned Gunnison sage-grouse habitat assessments in Dry Creek Basin, CO, to monitor and track several vegetation variables. This effort has been ongoing since 2007. In 2014, changes were implemented that would help make our effort to monitor Gunnison sage-grouse habitat more consistent with the BLM Sage-Grouse Habitat Assessment Framework.
- Prepared reports at the end of each field season detailing the work completed during the course of the year.
- Reported accomplishments in Wildlife, Fisheries and Rare Plants Management System (WFRP-MS), a database to catalog individual projects, species, areas, costs, and time frames for district reporting and public disclosure.
- Inspected completion, adequacy and project progress as a Contracting Officer Representative (COR) project inspector. COR responsibilities involved making sure that contracting specifications and project objectives were communicated to contractors and completed to contract standards in a timely fashion. The projects inspected were intended to improve habitat for deer, elk, Gunnison sage-grouse, desert bighorn sheep and pronghorn.
- Represented the wildlife department as a safety committee member, addressing issues and concerns to maintain a safe working environment for the office and all coworkers.
- Worked extensively with ArcMap 10, Trimble Juno 5Bs, Garmin GPSs, Microsoft Office, Quicktime, GovTrip and Microsoft Outlook to complete work.

U.S. Department of Agriculture - Forest Service

San Juan National Forest, Dolores-Mancos District

January 2011-March 2012 Biological Technician Supervisor (GS-0404-06, 18/8 appointment) Supervisor – Ivan Messinger; Phone: 970-882-6804

- Planned, organized and completed wildlife surveys and projects on both FS and BLM lands focusing on a myriad of wildlife species.
- Supervised wildlife department BLM field crew personnel, a job that required professional people skills, flexibility and mentoring.
- Worked hard to provide a safe working environment.
- Maintained all field equipment, including snowmobiles, ATVs and vehicles.
- Reviewed applications, interviewed and hired employees, interns and volunteers.
- Worked to educate and connect elementary school children and the community to the environment, as well as to the mission, goals and objectives of the FS and BLM.
- Updated, maintained, set up and downloaded Wildlife Acoustic's SM2 bat acoustic recorders, to identify sites that required bat accessible mine closures as a part of the Abandoned Mine Lands (AML) initiative. Bat calls were analyzed using Sonobat 3.0 bat call analysis software.
- Conducted Gunnison sage-grouse lek counts to determine population trends.
- Met on a monthly basis with local biologists to discuss future projects and ideas, as well as current projects and problems.
- Used both Microsoft Access and ArcMap 10 to manage wildlife and plant databases.

U.S. Department of the Interior - Bureau of Land Management

Dolores, Colorado (as of 2012 the Tres Rios District)

March 2009-January 2011

Biological Technician (GS-0404-05)

Supervisor: Eric Freels: 970-263-5828

- Planned and implemented Gunnison sage-grouse population augmentation in Dry Creek Basin and Dove Creek, CO.
- Organized the day-to-day activities for the Dolores Public Lands Office Wildlife and Fisheries Program technician crew.
- Designed and implemented a habitat mapping project that focused on inventorying hydro-morphology and vegetation, to determine potential for future habitat improvement projects.
- Prepared reports at the end of the research season outlining research and results of the data collected.
- Conducted regional goshawk surveys to determine regional occupancy and population in FS Region 2.

U.S. Department of Agriculture-Forest Service

San Juan National Forest, Dolores-Mancos District

May-October, 2008

Biological Science Technician (GS-0404-04)

Supervisor: Eric Freels: 970-263-5828

- Conducted surveys for: Mexican spotted-owls, southwestern willow flycatchers, northern goshawks, long-nosed leopard lizards and several other herpetofuana species, several humming bird species, Abert's squirrels and boreal owls.
- Observed and collected data for a national database, Wildlife, on approximately 30 threatened, endangered, sensitive and management indicator species as part of a national fauna collection effort.
- Collected data on Gunnison sage-grouse habitats using line transect and Daubenmire data collection techniques.
- Electroshocked 1000 m stretches of the lower Dolores River to sample for native and game fish species.
- Constructed and installed beaver management devices in impacted wetland areas.

Relevant Training and Certifications

- Rocky Mountain Region Biological Assessment/Biological Evaluation Training Course, 2011
- Current Wilderness First Responder 2011; Refresher 2014
- HR Management: What Supervisors and Managers Need to Know Training, 2011
- Southwestern Willow Flycatcher Survey Training with the Fish and Wildlife Service, 2009.
- Firefighter Type 2 Certified and Sawyer Apprentice Certified.
- Vehicle certifications: 4x4 training, Defensive Driving training, ATV training, snowmobile training and trailer towing certified.

Other Professional Experience

Four Corners Recycling Initiative

Montezuma County, Colorado

June 2013 – Present

Board Member

- Provided insight into how to best meet the recycling needs in the Four Corners area at no financial burden to local residents and businesses.
- Coordinated with local entities to provide recycling to residents.
- Planned and marketed events and fundraisers.
- Provided social media and web support.

Durango Shade Company

Durango, Colorado

November 2014 – Present (During Furlough) Web Developer and Business Consultant

- Designed and built the Durango Shade Company website (http://durangoshadecompany.com) from scratch, building a template for the owner to input content and images.
- Consulted on how to best organize and present information to customers.

References:

Eric Freels

District Wildlife Biologist Grand Valley Ranger District, Grand Mesa, Uncompaghre and Gunnison National Forests Grand Junction, Colorado 970-263-5828 erickfreels@fs.fed.us

Penny Wu

District Ranger Arapaho and Roosevelt National Forest and Pawnee National Grassland Idaho Springs, Colorado 303-567-3001 pwu@fs.fed.us

Jim White

Aquatic Biologist Colorado Parks and Wildlife Durango, Colorado 970-375-6712 j.white@state.co.us

Tom Fresques

Fish Biologist Colorado Southwest District, BLM Silt, Colorado 970-876-9078 t1fresqu@blm.gov

Marlin Boyer

Owner Durango Shade Company Durango, Colorado 970-497-9001 durangoshadecompany@gmail.com